<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Research Software Science: Expanding the Impact of Research Software Engineering</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lorena</forename><surname>Barba</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Sandia National Laboratories</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saint John&apos;s University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Heroux</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Sandia National Laboratories</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Saint John&apos;s University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Research Software Science: Expanding the Impact of Research Software Engineering</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">95567BC2920AA9776BA8E05333B25FAD</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/MCSE.2023.3260475</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2026-03-09T17:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Software plays a central role in scientific discovery. Improving how we develop and use software for research can have both broad and deep impacts on a spectrum of challenges and opportunities society faces today. The emergence of the Research Software Engineer (RSE) as a role correlates with the growing complexity of scientific challenges and the diversity of software team skills. In this paper, we describe research software science (RSS), an idea related to RSE, and particularly suited to research software teams. RSS promotes the use of scientific methodologies to explore and establish broadly applicable knowledge. Using RSS, we can pursue sustainable, repeatable, and reproducible software improvements that positively impact research software toward improved scientific discovery.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESEARCH SOFTWARE ENGINEER (RSE)</head><p>has emerged as an identity for many members of the research software community <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. For many years, RSE functions were needed on scientific teams but only recently has there been the growth in awareness of the importance of these skills and the people who possess them, leading to a long-overdue and explicit recognition that RSE staff require stable career paths and communities of their own, beyond solely being part of a particular scientific team. RSE job functions rely on the premise that there are better and worse ways to produce soft-ware for use in scientific research. Often, RSEs read the existing software engineering literature to keep informed about, adapt, and adopt evolving practices and tools. They also carry techniques and experience from project to project. These translational strategies are intrinsically valuable and are a part of the fundamental value proposition that RSEs bring to the scientific community.</p><p>In this paper, we present the concept of research software science (RSS): applying the scientific method to understanding and improving how software is developed and used for research (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). We argue that RSS is an important complement to RSE efforts, providing another avenue to enhance the impact of RSE efforts beyond translational activities. Furthermore, RSS leverages the innate scientific sensibilities of the research communities to which RSE members belong. In other words, while it is appropriate to apply a scientific approach to understanding and improving how any kind of software is developed and used, it is particularly apt to use this approach for research software. Finally, by emphasizing a scientific approach to improving software activities, research funding organizations and research institutions can more readily justify investments in advancing how their sponsored software projects improve the practice of developing and using software for research, as can be seen by the recent US Department of Energy sponsorship of the Workshop on the Science of Scientific-Software Development and Use <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> in December 2021.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p>The development and use of software are fundamental to numerous areas of scientific research <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Many scientists write, modify, and use software to gain insight and prove scientific results. At the same time, formal software engineering techniques and knowledge that are widely adopted in other software development domains are not as commonly used in research software projects. In our experience and as reported in Carver et. al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, research software development approaches are more informal, particularly in the upstream activities of requirements, analysis, and design.</p><p>One challenge to investing in improved software practices and processes for science is the perception by some that a focus on improving software skills falls under the category of engineering, not science. There is a perception that software engineering-refining repeated practices for more efficiency-is not something that a scientific research funding portfolio should support as a fundamental element.</p><p>From this perspective, the best that research software teams can do is spend modest amounts of time learning practices from the mainstream software engineering literature and use them unchanged or with modest adaptation in their own software development. While the RSE movement is improving the situation for larger scientific teams, in our experience, the current status results in only moderate success-and sometimes even failure. Best practices distilled from larger, more mainstream software domains may be ill-suited for research software teams.</p><p>The growth of the RSE community is a strong sign that these perceptions are changing, and software engineering is increasingly recognized as essential skill set on a diverse scientific software team. Even so, there is another opportunity to improve our ability to develop software and improve its usability.</p><p>In this article, we propose that the scientific method-which is central to scientific efforts using research software-can also be used to study and improve the development and use of research software. Looking at the development and use of software for research through a scientific lens enables us to apply a scientific approach to understand and improve software as a tool for research. In other words, research software development and use are the subjects of our scientific study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Software Science: Definition</head><p>Research software science (RSS) is defined <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> as applying the scientific method to understanding and improving how software is developed and used for research. RSS involves the use of formal observation and experimentation to obtain and disseminate knowledge through repeatable and reproducible processes. Understanding and improving software development and use involves obtaining data to detect correlation, designing experiments to identify cause and effect, and publishing results for broad impact.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding agencies and software engineering</head><p>Numerous members of the research software community have expressed concern that software products receive insufficient direct funding for sustainability. Funding efforts by the US National Science Foundation (NSF) acknowledge this problem with specific programs for software support such as the CSSI program <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> and institutes such as MolSSI <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. The US Department of Energy has had similar efforts, for example, the SciDAC program <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and the Exascale Computing Project <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. However, the fundamental issue that NSF, DOE and others face is that they are primarily scientific agencies, limiting their abilities to provide sustained software engineering funding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RSS and software funding and recognition</head><p>By cultivating RSS as a scientific approach that complements an engineering approach, we can more easily highlight that software engineering studies are often scientific. Explicitly focusing on a scientific approach to improving research software gives scientific funding agencies unambiguous opportunities to fund this kind of work, promoting further advancements in scientific software work. Furthermore, elevating the status of software engineering to a scientific discipline will help to attract more software engineering talent to the research software community and increase respect for software work within research organizations, key challenges identified in Maimone et. al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Science applied to research software</head><p>As stated above, the primary objective of research software science is to apply the scientific method to understanding the development and use of research software. This pursuit has strong technical, social, and cognitive components. While many people have realized the importance of the technical component of research software development and use, fewer people have focused on the social and cognitive elements, and even fewer have applied a scientific approach to studying and improving research software team interactions or the concerns of individual members.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Technical component:</head><p>Software is used in the majority of research pursuits <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Examples include modeling and simulation of scientific theories; the gathering, analysis, and understanding of scientific data; and related pursuits. These research activities typically require years of education in a research domain and ongoing community engagement to contribute to and keep abreast of discoveries and approaches. For example, to develop and use computational fluid dynamics (CFD) research software, one must complete years of study in mathematics, physics, and engineering and then continue the study of CFD and related fields even when developing and using the software.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Social component:</head><p>Development and use of scientific software are typically a team effort, increasingly involving more people and more diverse roles. In the case of CFD, a team may collaborate with a structural dynamics simulation team to study aeroelasticitythe coupled study of CFD and structural dynamics to account for the inter-dependence of how blades bend and airflow behavior changes-in the modeling of wind turbines. Together these teams may need to use advanced parallel computers, requiring additional skills on the team. As teams grow by aggregation of skills, the interactions, workflows, and tools that are used will play a large part in the effectiveness of a research software team. Furthermore, scientific software teams are often composed of both developers and users <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cognitive component:</head><p>Improving our approaches to developing and using research software typically requires learning. In our experience, scientists tend to enjoy solving problems. Framing change as a problem or puzzle to be solved can be effective in engaging scientists. Posing improvement goals in a descriptive, more than prescriptive, way enables scientists to be part of the creative process. More generally, leveraging knowledge cognitive sciences can improve our ability to understand how developers and users of research software approach their work and interact with each other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Social and cognitive sciences focus</head><p>Applying the scientific method to research software teams necessarily involves the social and cognitive sciences. Observations, interviews, data mining, and similar techniques provide the raw materials for analyzing and gaining an understanding of important correlations-and ultimately, one hopes, identifying cause and effect-between behaviors, situations, and outcomes.</p><p>While the software engineering literature addresses the social and cognitive elements of software development and use, research software teams take on considerable risks by adopting published team practices without scrutiny or adaptation. In our experience, many published team practices are not sufficiently informed by the dynamics and requirements of research software development and use. To better understand when and how existing software methodologies are appropriate and to develop new approaches for research software, we need the skills and tools of social and cognitive sciences applied to research software teams and individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RSS not just an extension of RSE</head><p>As mentioned, the software engineering literature provides ample material dedicated to the social and cognitive elements of software teams. Some of this literature is scientific in nature, but much of it is anecdotal, based on years of experience from seasoned software professionals. These writers produce generalized recommendations from specific experiences, often with benefit to other developers and users.</p><p>It is reasonable to argue that RSS is a modest extension of RSE. There is some truth to this, especially to the extent RSE team members experiment with new mental models, tools, and processes. However, in our experience, this experimentation is seldom a formal, repeatable, or reproducible process designed to generate sharable knowledge. Instead, we believe it is fruitful to consider RSS as a new identifiable element within an existing RSE organization. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> shows a notional research-develop-deploy pipeline where the challenges of supporting research software within the deploy phase inform the questions in the research phase that are then used to inform the develop phase and lead to new deployable capabilities.</p><p>Fred Brooks, author of the popular book The Mythical Man-Month is often quoted as saying, "A scientist builds in order to learn; an engineer learns in order to build." Engineers want an improved tool or process. They identify a few possibilities, test, select the best, and move on. There is only incidental team memory and little focus on dissemination. Scientists want to understand underlying principles, correlation, and cause-andeffect. They design studies, capture data, analyze results and publish.</p><p>The software engineering community certainly performs research, but this research is not always directly applicable to research software. Furthermore, especially in the research community, we should call this kind of work what it is: science.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Why now: Multidisciplinary direction of science</head><p>Many important efforts in science require strong multidisciplinary teams. As noted in the aeroelasticity example above, we see that research software is increasingly incorporating multiscale  As efforts proceeded, the need for new mathematics and more efficient computer science algorithms and data structures emerged. As software products grew in size, complexity and coupling, the need for data management and software engineering expertise emerged. Presently, the growing complexity of scientific software projects increases the value of investing in cognitive and social sciences. and multiphysics features, equation-driven and data-driven approaches, involving modeling, simulation, and data analysis. Adding a scientific approach to understanding the development and use of research software establishes one more dimension in the pursuit of better scientific approaches and is especially appropriate given the growing diversity of scientific teams and the need to understand and optimize team interactions and output. Historically, we can see the expansion of skillsets needed by leading research software communities, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Trends in scientific software that increase the value of RSS</head><p>The technology community is seeing the growing importance of considering human factors in product development <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. In addition, software design and development platforms are becoming increasingly sophisticated, reducing the cost of creating products. For example, artificial intelligence (AI)-based tools that assist in generating source code, testing infrastructure, and more, are available to assist in producing software.</p><p>With the increased emphasis on improving the usability of software and the reduced cost of producing it, skills in eliciting and analyzing requirements, and user-centered design become relatively more important than development skills. More time will be spent on the upstream and higher-level activities of what the product should be than on making the product. Because of these trends, we have an opportunity to place more emphasis on purpose and design, resulting in software systems adapted to fit scientists, broadening usability, accessibility, and impact.</p><p>As part of the trends we observe, software engineering practices such as focusing on user experience (UX) can make more sense in the research software development process to address the growing size and complexity of scientific teams and environments. Research software science can play a large role in guiding these UX activities, providing a scientific foundation for long-term and sustainable impact. One notable UX opportunity for scientific software is to study the dynamics of teams where the users are also the primary developers, a common situation for research software teams but an atypical situation for most UX methodologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Development and use of research software are rich and dynamic pursuits, worthy of scientific study in their own right. Viewing the pursuit of better research software as a scientific problem opens the door to applying scientific approaches to assist in making our software development and use even more effective and efficient. Cultivating the concepts of RSS should facilitate direct funding for software efforts by research organizations such as NSF and DOE and help elevate respect for software efforts at research institutions. Finally, RSS should lead to a qualitative improvement in the development and use of research software, just as the scientific method has led to a qualitative improvement in many other fields.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Research software science (RSS) is proposed as a complementary approach to RSE efforts for improving how software is developed and used for research. RSS leverages the inherent appreciation for scientific methodologies present in the research community, providing another source of information for RSE practitioners to leverage.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,118.81,57.05,435.20,210.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. One model for integrating software science staff into an existing research software engineering team is to consider a research-develop-deploy pipeline. Opportunities for improving the development and use of research software approaches come from understanding the challenges faced in deploying existing software products. These challenges become the research problems for study and later become new approaches to develop and deploy.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,59.04,57.05,435.20,224.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Early use of software for scientific discovery was generally small-scale, developed by a team of domain scientists.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,115.51,337.07,322.25,165.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0">Computing in Science and EngineeringPublished by the IEEE Computer Society © 2023 IEEE</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1">Computing in Science and Engineering</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_2">March/April 2023</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>The original idea of Research Software Science presented in this article was first delivered as a white paper at the 2019 Collegeville Workshop on Sustainable Scientific Software (CW3S19) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, then revised and extended for a blog post <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, cross-posted on the BSSw and URSSI websites. We thank St. John's University for the on-site and virtual resources used to conduct the Collegeville Workshops on Scientific Software <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> that were the genesis of the concept of Research Software Science.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bernholdt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Cary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Heroux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lois</forename><forename type="middle">Curfman</forename><surname>Mcinnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2172/1846008</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2172/1846008" />
		<title level="m">The Science of Scientific-Software Development and Use. brochure from the basic research needs workshop</title>
				<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2022</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of the state of the practice for research software in the united states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nick</forename><surname>Jeffrey C Carver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Karthik</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sandra</forename><surname>Ram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gesing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PeerJ Comput Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e963</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022-05">May 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://beta.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/cyberinfrastructure-sustained-scientific" />
		<title level="m">Cyberinfrastructure for Sustained Scientific Innovation (CSSI)</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-02-20">February 20, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Science Foundation</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">posts/research-software-science-ascientific-approach-to-understanding-and-improvinghow-we-develop-and-use-software-for-research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mike</forename><surname>Heroux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://bssw.io/blog" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Research Software Science: A Scientific Approach to Understanding and Improving How We Develop and Use Software for Research. blog article in Better Scientific Software, online</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-09-25">September 25 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">softwaresaved/software in research survey 2014: Software in research survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Hettrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-02">Feb 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2014-12-04-its-impossible-conduct-research-without-software-say-7-out-10-uk-researchers" />
		<title level="m">Software Sustainability Institute. It&apos;s impossible to conduct research without software, say 7 out of 10 uk researchers</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-02-22">2014. 22 Feb 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing the US Research Computing and Data (RCD) Workforce</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christina</forename><surname>Maimone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Scott</forename><surname>Yockel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Timothy</forename><surname>Middelkoop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ashley</forename><surname>Stauffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Reidy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Practice and Experience in Advanced Research Computing, PEARC &apos;22</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Michael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Heroux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://collegeville.github.io/CW3S19/" />
		<title level="m">Workshop on Sustainable Scientific Software</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Collegeville Workshops Home Page</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Michael</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Heroux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://collegeville.github.io/Workshops/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Molssi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://molssi.org" />
		<title level="m">The Molecular Sciences Software Institute</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-02-20">February 20, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://exascaleproject.org/" />
		<title level="m">Department of Energy. DOE Exascale Computing Project</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-02-20">February 20, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://www.scidac.gov/" />
		<title level="m">Department of Energy. DOE Scientific Discovery through Advanced Computing (SciDAC) Program</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-02-20">February 20, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://society-rse.org" />
		<title level="m">Society of Research Software Engineering. RSE Society Homepage</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gillian</forename><surname>Tett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Anthrovision: A New Way to See in Business and Life</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Avid Reader Press/Simon &amp; Schuster</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://us-rse.org" />
		<title level="m">The United States Research Software Engineer Association. US-RSE Homepage</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
